さて　トリルラン卿
Very well, Sir Trillram.
My Landing Castle is ready to retire for dinner,
我が揚陸城は蝕に入る故　間もなくこのレーザー通信は途切れる
so this laser comm link will end shortly.
Let us be brief.
手短に済まそうか
ネズミ退治の状況は？
Have our rats been exterminated?
You awake?
気が付きましたか
ったい
Don't do that.
あぁ　いけない　まだ安静にしていてください
You need rest.
ここは？
Where am I?
学校ですよ　敵にはまだ気付かれていません
In the school.
The enemy hasn't realized we're here yet.
We should be safe for the time being.
ひとまず逃げ切る事は出来ました
Where are the others?
他のみんなは？
You mean Inaho and his friends?
伊奈帆君達ですか
They say they're going to fight...
戦うと言っています
ここにある装備で
with the equipment we have here...
あの火星カタフラクトと
against the Martian Cataphract.
Your selfless dream
kimi ga miru yume wa
君が見る夢は　古いインクで紙に書いた祈りのよう
is like a prayer written on paper with yellowing ink
kimi ga miru yume wa
furui inku de kami ni kaita inori no you
is like a prayer written on paper with yellowing ink
Your fragile hands seek support,
chiisana sono te ga sugaru mono mo
小さなその手が　縋るものも　今はまだ何処にも無い
and yet have nothing at all to cling to
chiisana sono te ga sugaru mono mo
ima wa mada doko ni mo nai
and yet have nothing at all to cling to
But even so, I want to guard
sore demo kimi no yuku michi wo
それでも君の行く道を
the path you walk
sore demo kimi no yuku michi wo
kirei na mono wa kirei na mama de
奇麗なものは奇麗なままで　守り続けたいと思うよ
the path you walk
kirei na mono wa kirei na mama de
mamoritsuzuketai to omou yo
in all my beauty
sora to mizu ga hoshi wo somete
I can see our skies and seas in the stars
空と水が星を染めて
sora to mizu ga hoshi wo somete
I can see our skies and seas in the stars
awaku niji wo egaite chitte
before they fall to make a rainbow
淡く虹を描いて散って
awaku niji wo egaite chitte
before they fall to make a rainbow
mabushii yoru kimi ga utau
Light tears through the night and you sing
眩しい夜　君が歌う
mabushii yoru kimi ga utau
koe wa doko made todoku no darou
How far will your voice travel?
声は何処まで届くのだろう
koe wa doko made todoku no darou
How far will your voice travel?
akogare no sumau aoi hoshi no hikari
This is the light of the blue planet I admire,
憧れの住まう蒼い星のひかり
akogare no sumau aoi hoshi no hikari
This is the light of the blue planet I admire,
the light that we love helplessly
tada bokura wa koi wo shite
ただ僕らは恋をして
the light that we love helplessly
tatta hitotsu no mirai no tame ni
We sacrifice all we have at our disposal
たったひとつの未来の為に
tatta hitotsu no mirai no tame ni
We sacrifice all we have at our disposal
ima no subete kanadetemiru
for the only future we have left
今の全て奏でてみる
ima no subete kanadetemiru
for the only future we have left
tobitatsu yo
Let us fly
飛び立つよ　まだ暗い空へ
tobitatsu yo
Let us fly
mada kurai sora he
into the blackened sky
Hey, what's the meaning of this?
おい　どういう事だ　こいつは
Orders from HQ.
本部からの指令です
We've been ordered to abandon this base once all civilians have been evacuated.
市民の避難が完了し次第　この基地を破棄して撤退しろと
まだ戦ってる仲間がいるんだぞ
We have someone still fighting out there!
You are the only survivor,
生き残ったのはあなた一人ですよ
Lieutenant Marito Kouichirou.
鞠戸孝一郎大尉
あんたは？
Who're you?
ダルザナ・マグバレッジ
Darzana Magbaredge.
Captain of the Watatsumi, an amphibious assault ship
attached to the Fourth Escort Fleet.
第四護衛艦隊所属　強襲揚陸艦　「海神」の艦長です
こちらは不見咲カオル副長
This is Mizusaki Kaoru, my XO.
北地区にまだ仲間が残っています
One of my subordinates is still fighting in the northern sector.
The only reason this place isn't rubble already is because she's holding them off!
ここがまだ無事なのは　彼女が足止めをしているからです
Who is "she"?
彼女？
Warrant Officer Kaizuka Yuki!
界塚ユキ准尉です
新芦原全域に電波妨害が発生しています
Radio communications are being jammed
across all of Shin-awara.
We can't use our GPS either.
GPSも利かない
救援に向かおうにも位置情報を特定できません
Even if we sent out a rescue mission, we wouldn't be able to direct them.
But...
しかし
Our primary objective is to escort and protect the ferry carrying the refugees.
避難民を乗せたフェリーを護衛し　誘導するのが我々の任務です
Some of them haven't made it to the ferry!
逃げ遅れた民間人だって残ってる
I can't find some of my kids on the passenger list!
乗客名簿にはガキ共の名前も無かった
俺の生徒達だ
My students!
Very well.
いいでしょう　司令部に救援部隊の編成を申請します
I'll request permission from HQ to send out a rescue party.
揚陸艇を1隻だけ残しましょう
You can have one landing craft.
However, if you can't find enough people to crew her,
ですが　操船クルーの数が揃わなかったら
you'll have to abandon this endeavor.
その時は　諦めなさい
I know you're in there, Nao!
なお君　いるんでしょ
Nao!
なお君
I am.
入ってます
I'm here because we have to talk!
知ってるわよ　だから来たの
Do you have any idea what you're doing?
あなた　自分達がやろうとしてる事を分かってるの
I'm perfectly aware that this is crazy.
無茶なのは百も承知だよ
ならどうして
Then why?!
I don't know why, but that Martian is obsessed with hunting us.
あの火星人　どういうわけか僕らを狙ってムキになってる
Therefore, his attacks won't spread to the city proper
or the harbor while we hold out here.
つまり　ここで僕らが粘っていれば
市街や港に攻撃が及ぶ事はない
幸いこの辺りの住民は避難が済んでるしね
As luck would have it, this entire area
has already been evacuated.
But that doesn't mean—
だからって…
起助が死んだ
Okisuke is dead.
"Adapt your plans to fit the situation!"
「判断は臨機応変
"If you have to, trust your gut and make the call!"
いざとなれば自分を信じて決断する」
Isn't that what you're always telling me?
ユキ姉　いつも言ってたよね
I think this is one of those times.
きっと　今がその時だと思う
私がやるわ
I'll do it.
No. You need to rest and heal.
けが人には任せられない
Nao!
なお君
皆不安がってるんだ
Everyone's so nervous.
I want you to look after them.
だから　ユキ姉が守ってあげて欲しい
Cheer up the ones that are scared, and make them feel at ease.
怯えてる人達を励まして　安心させて欲しい
That's something that only you can do.
それこそ　僕達には出来ない事だ
Your Highness...
姫様…　誰よりも平和を望んでおられた方だったのに
You wished for peace more than anyone, and yet...
Who would commit this atrocity?
一体誰が
つまり貴公は　ネズミを殺し損なうのみならず
So not only did you fail to kill the last rat,
but you also let its trail go cold?
その行方まで見失ったと？
If I may interject, Lord Saazbaum.
恐れながら　ザーツバルム様
このトリルラン　まだ彼奴を取り逃がしたわけではありませぬ
She has not escaped my grasp just yet.
Oh?
There is only one place she could have escaped through the tunnel into which she fled.
奴が逃げ込んだトンネルから移動できる範囲は限られています
Namely, the northern district of Shin-awara!
すなわち　この新芦原北側区画
The moment she pokes her nose from her hole,
痺れを切らして穴蔵から顔を出した刹那
my Nilokeras will catch her
with its hawk-like gaze and—
我がニロケラスの誇る鷹の目を以って即座に…
Fool.
たわけ
Do you think we have time to wait upon her leisure?
根比べをしている余裕があると思うか
ネズミの居場所が確かなら構わぬ
Knowing her rough location is adequate.
その街もろとも消し飛ばしてしまえばいい
We can simply raze the entire city to the ground.
I will order a meteor strike.
隕石爆撃を行う
L-Lord Saazbaum! Count Cruhteo's Landing Castle is too close!
ザ…ザーツバルム様
しかし　ここはクルーテオ卿の揚陸城に近すぎます
Would he not view this as an act of aggression?
彼に対する攻撃と見なされるのでは
A necessary sacrifice.
背に腹は代えられん
I will require several hours to adjust my orbit.
軌道調整に数時間かかる
その間　そなたはネズミが他所へ逃げぬよう　監視を続行せよ
Continue your observation,
lest the rat scurry away in the interim.
ははっ
Understood!
それは？
What's that?
I summarized all we know
about the Martian Cataphract.
あの火星カタフラクトについて　まとめてみたんだ
The shells you fired were all absorbed
rather than ricocheting off the armor, right?
あいつ　ユキ姉が撃った弾を跳ね返すんじゃなくて
全部吸い込んでたよね
How's the signal?
電波はどうだ？
Barely strong enough.
ギリギリ
Such impertinence!
ちょこざいな
And... go!
せーのっ
It's not just shells, either.
弾だけじゃない
Any sensor pings that hit it are simply absorbed.
アクティブセンサーの信号も　あいつに当てると帰ってこない
What does that mean?
どういう事？
Infrared, echolocation, radar...
赤外線も音波探知もレーダーも　全部ダメ
All useless.
No echo.
エコーが戻らなかったんです
It absorbs not only kinetic energy
but also electromagnetic radiation.
運動エネルギーだけじゃなく　電波もレーザーも吸収される
きっとそれが　あの壁の特性なんだと思う
I'm sure that's what gives that wall
all those fancy properties.
壁？
Wall?
あいつの表面を覆っている　エネルギーフィールドだよ
The energy field that covers its surface.
バリアって呼んでもいい
Call it a barrier if you want.
バリア
A barrier?
It absorbs all matter, light, sound, and radio waves that touch it.
物質も光も音も電波も　触れるもの全てを吸収するバリア
でもさ　それなら　あいつはどうやって　バリアのこちら側を見てるんだろう
But in that case, how can he see anything of the outside world?
The barrier completely isolates him
from all outside knowledge.
外からの情報を全部バリアで遮断してるんだよ
I don't think he can see or hear anything from our side of the barrier.
もしかしたらあいつは　バリア越しにこっちを見る事も聞く事もできないのかも
Absorption
Barrier
僕の考えではあのバリアの裏側は真っ黒に見えるはず
If my theory is correct, the inside of that barrier should appear perfectly black to him.
Light
Sound
EM Waves
でも　だったらどうしてあいつの攻撃は当たるの
But how does he hit us, then?
Yeah.
確かに　見てねえんならどうやって狙いを付けてんだ
How can he fight if he can't see where he's aiming?
His attacks were pinpoint accurate, even through buildings.
あいつは　逃げる僕達をビルの向こうから正確に攻撃してきた
But despite pursuing us madly, he immediately gave up the chase when we entered the tunnel.
でも　あれだけしつこく追って来たくせに
僕らがトンネルに入った途端　あっさり諦めた
きっと　バリアの外側を見ていたのはあいつじゃない
I bet he has something outside of the barrier
to act as his eyes and ears.
あいつは視界を確保するために
He probably has cameras in place that provide him
with a field of vision, likely from above.
恐らく上空に別のカメラを用意してるんだと思う
Something like this.
こんな感じ
This is how he was able to chase us
no matter where we went,
だから　どんなに引き離されても僕達を追ってこれたし
and why he was hesitant to enter a tunnel.
トンネルに入るのを嫌がった
バリアを張りながら前を見る事ができないからだ
With his barrier up, he wouldn't be able to see a thing.
今もあいつは空から僕達を監視しているはずだ
He's probably searching for us
through his aerial cameras as we speak.
Makes sense.
なるほどな
逆に言えば　こうして屋根の下にいる限りは　安全ってわけだ
It also means we're safe as long as we stay under cover like we are now.
However, he'll spot us the instant we step outside.
でも　外に出た途端に見つかる
We'll probably only get one chance at this.
たぶんチャンスは一回限りだね
Oh, come on. Where are the backup batteries?
バックアップバッテリーがもう無いじゃない
Whose turn was it to check them this week?
誰よ　今週のチェック担当は
鞠戸め
Damn it, Marito...
Hey, Inaho.
ねえ　伊奈帆
We three are going out in the Cats.
カットで出るのが俺たち三人
So we need two more to drive the decoy truck, right?
さらに囮トラックに二人は必要だろう
Who do you want to ask?
誰に頼む？
私に　お手伝いさせてください
Please.
Let me help.
姫さ…
Princ—
北欧美人
The Scandinavian babe...
I feel it is my duty to share this predicament.
These tribulations.
この窮地　この試練　私には引き受ける務めがあると感じます
中二病？
Too many fantasy novels?
どうかぜひ
Please.
あいつは父を殺した
He killed my father.
私にも協力させて
Let me help too.
こっちも命がけだぜ
Our lives are on the line here.
I know.
分かってる
任せて
You can count on me.
We'll do it tomorrow morning.
決行は明朝　日の出と共に出発しよう
Let's set out at first light.
あの火星カタフラクトを撃退する
We'll drive off that Martian Cataphract.
Still at it?
まだやってるの
Why aren't you asleep, Inko?
韻子こそ　寝ないの
The meeting room's too cold.
会議室　結構寒くて
空調切ってるからね
Yeah, the climate control's off, since we want to minimize any signs of human presence.
人の気配はなるべく消しておきたいから
Calm's sleeping like a log, though.
カームは絶賛睡眠中だけどね
Hope he doesn't catch cold.
風邪引かなきゃいいけど
何？
What?
だって　風邪の心配とか
Seriously? You're worried about him catching cold?
明日　死んじゃうかもしれないのに
You guys might die tomorrow.
ごめん
Sorry.
It's okay.
別にさ　怖い物知らずってわけじゃないよ
It's not like I don't get scared, you know.
助けられると思ったんだ
I thought we were saved, back there.
でもあんなにあっさり…
But they wiped out the soldiers like flies, without a moment's hesitation.
あんなに簡単に…
きっとその時が来ても　覚悟する暇さえ無いんだろう
If that happens to us, we won't even have time to say our prayers.
What will we regret as our lives
flash before our eyes?
その瞬間にどんな後悔をするのか
そう思いながら　ただじっと待ってるだけなんて　耐えられない
When I think about that,
I can't just sit and wait.
I bet Calm feels the same way.
僕も　たぶん　カームも
If you're having second thoughts, Inko...
もし韻子が嫌なら…
No, I'm okay.
大丈夫
I'll rest up for tomorrow, then.
明日に備えて　もう寝る
Good.
伊奈帆
Inaho.
You take care not to catch cold too.
風邪　引かないでね
韻子も
Same to you, Inko.
Allow me to thank you all again.
改めて礼を言う
We five will now set out to Shin-awara's northern district to rescue the remaining soldiers and civilians.
これより我々五名は　新芦原市北地区築に残る友軍
及び避難民の救出作戦を遂行する
I hope you can use one more.
一名追加してください
マグバレッジ艦長
Captain Magbaredge?
フェリー護衛は不見咲副長に一任しました
I've entrusted XO Mizusaki with escorting the ferry.
作戦完了後　合流する手筈です
We'll meet up again after their mission.
急ぎましょう
We should hurry.
あなたに興味があります
You interest me,
Lieutenant Marito Kouichirou.
鞠戸孝一郎大尉
Look at that!
見てください　あれ
Signal rounds.
信号弾　赤球3発
Three reds?
学校の方ですよ
That's the direction of the school!
戦闘開始だと
"Commencing attack"?
ネズミめ
Little rat.
方を付けるぞ
I'll squash you for good!
出発します　ついて来てください
This is it! Come with me!
Damn, there's so much on the sides of the road!
もう　道幅　きつい
Who cares? No one's here to dock you points!
構うな　今日は減点なんてされねえよ
Found him! Ten o'clock!
見つけた　10時の方向
出たな　ダンゴムシ
There you are, you giant pillbug.
Commence operation.
作戦開始
Damn it!
おのれ　まさか…
It can't be!
He's stopped moving!
奴の動きが止まった
Inaho was right!
伊奈帆の言った通り
ねえ　セーフティーを外す　構える　撃つ
Listen.
Release the safety, grip the stock, and fire.
簡単でしょ
Simple, right?
Mangy rats!
このクソネズミ共が
You all right, Kaizuka?
無事か　界塚
鞠戸大尉
Lieutenant Marito!
Sir Trillram!
トリルラン卿
これは一体…
What's going on?
Hey, this wasn't part of the plan!
聞いてないぞこんな
The truck!
トレーラーだ
Sir?
位置を教えろ　奴はどこだ
Tell me its position!
Where is it?!
T-To your southwest, heading toward the city center.
な…南西方向　街の中心部に向かっているようです
He's plowing through everything!
あいつ　滅茶苦茶
Cover me! That bat thing's
blowing away the smokescreen!
援護してくれ
あのコウモリ　あいつの気流で煙幕が乱れる
落とさねえと
We gotta shoot it down!
Hold it, Calm!
ちょっと　カーム
地球の　カタフラクト
A Terran Cataphract!
F-Forgive me!
す…すみません
カーム
Calm!
しまった
Damn it!
You okay?
大丈夫？
Yeah. My stabilizer's shot,
but I can force it to keep going.
スタビライザーはやられたけど　ギリギリ走れる
あいつには弾が当たるのね
Rockets seem to work on that one.
It's called a sky carrier.
スカイキャリア
A Vers tactical transport plane.
ヴァースの戦術輸送機です
As I understand, it has no special abilities or equipment beyond machine guns and missiles.
機銃やミサイル以外の特殊装備　能力は有していないと聞いています
煙幕を
Keep up the smokescreen.
はい
Right.
電圧チェック
Voltage, check.
油圧チェック
Oil pressure, check.
温度チェック
Temperature, check.
回転数ノーマー
RPM normal.
You
can
do
it,
Nao
Yu
フォース・フィードバック・チェッキング・プログラム　スタート
Force feedback checking program, start.
You
can
do
it,
Nao
Yu
エジェクションシート　正常
Ejection seat functional.
IFF confirmed.
IFF確認
戦術データリンク　アクティベート
Tactical datalink activated.
Here he comes.
おでましよ
Systems, all green.
システム　オールグリーン
Hold open.
ホールド　オープン
You're not getting away.
逃がさぬ
1,200 meters to our destination.
目的地まで1200メートル
合流予定時刻は93秒後です
Estimated time till rendezvous is 93 seconds.
時間を稼ぐ
I'll buy them some time.
Let me concentrate for a minute.
少し黙ってて
Are you playing with me?
私をコケにするか
手こずらせおって
I almost broke a sweat.
逃げて　あいつは私を…
Get out of here.
It's me he's after—
I will not.
いいえ　合流予定時刻まで　54秒
Estimated time till rendezvous is 54 seconds.
あとは私が
I'll take care of this.
Huh?
Coming to beg for your lives? How pathetic.
見苦しいな　今になって命乞いとは
Withdraw!
控えなさい
目に余る狼藉　許しません
I will not allow such senseless violence.
ヴァース第一王女の名において
Stop, in the name of the First Vers Princess!
Her Highness Asseylum Vers Allusia?
アセイラム・ヴァース・アリューシア姫殿下
まさか…
It can't be!
Leave at once, you ill-mannered knave!
下がりなさい　無礼者
This can't be!
馬鹿な　そんな馬鹿な
It's just not possible!
Fire all missiles!
全弾発射　目標　敵火星カタフラクト
Target the enemy Martian Cataphract!
How did you...
あなた一体…
Uh...
えっと…　マスターアームスイッチ
Activate master arm switch.
ファイアコントロール　ダンパー下ろして…
Locate fire control.
Lower the dampers—
韻子　急げ
Pick up the pace, Inko!
Oh, fine!
もう
You waste your time!
My Nilokeras' defense is impenetrable!
無駄だ　我がニロケラスは鉄壁の防御　貴様らなんぞに…
The likes of you could never—
Recalculating aim!
誤差修正　016　012
0-1-6, 0-1-2!
Fire!
ファイヤー
撃て撃て撃て撃て撃て
Fire, fire, fire, fire, fire!
The water!
水が…
おのれぇ
Damn you!
カーム
Calm.
ええと　あ…足の裏？
Uh... the soles of its feet?
Anything else?
他は
えっと
There!
見つけた
The water's not being absorbed!
水が吸い込まれない　背面装甲　インテーク右下　爪の隙間
The rear armor, below and to the right of the intake, between the claws!
馬鹿な
Impossible!
お前のバリアに隙間がある事は分かっていた
We knew there had to be gaps in your barrier.
例えば接地面　足の裏にバリアは張れない
Like the parts that touch the ground.
If you had a barrier under your feet, you wouldn't be able to stand.
そんな事をすればお前は立つ事すらできなくなる
お前のバリアはその無敵さゆえ　全身を覆いきる事ができないんだ
It's the very invincibility of your barrier that makes it impossible for you to cover yourself in it completely.
And another one of those gaps is the receiver for your external cameras.
外部カメラのデータ受信部　バリアの隙間の一つさ
友達の分だ
This is for my friend.
やったのか
Did they do it?
っしゃあ
Yes!
Impossible!
まさか…
The princess of Mars.
火星の…　プリンセス
本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigami.org)制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:つっちー  翻译:mam&低音子  校对:小可&zwx  时间轴:宋宋的黑猫  压制:河蟹
rei
Zero
0　始まりにも　終わりにも　変わる光
hajimari ni mo
Both the beginning
owari ni mo
and the end
kawaru hikari
see the changing of light
shita ni muketa mama
Back when I decided
下に向けたまま　かざすのを止めた　あの時
kazasu no wo yameta ano toki
that I would stop fooling myself and others,
LP no saizu no awanai uso bakari narabete
all I did was pile lie upon lie,
ALD noah
LP no saizu no awanai uso bakari narabete
all I did was pile lie upon lie,
サイズの合わない　嘘ばかり並べて
miushinai mizukara subete ni tsumazuita
with no chance to be comfortable with myself
見失い　自ら全てに　つまずいた
earth terasu a to a
Shine on Earth
AS　照らす　影と栄
kurikaesu count
Count again
繰り返すcount　明日の零時のサイン
asu no reiji no sign
The sign of twelve in the morning
lie mo die
Lie and die
LIVE or DIE
mienai hikari no sen
Under the sunlight,
見えない　光の線
ochiru dake de
just from that,
文字だけで　生kill-場所捨てて
kuruu basho subete
everything goes mad
namae mo nai soko ni
Even though I vainly seek answers
名前も居ない　そこに　答えを求めてても
kotae wo motometetemo
from that kind of nameless place,
kaze ni tokashita inochi no rei
I won't throw away my soul
風にとかした　命のRain　投げ捨てない
nagesutenai
as it is carried on the wind
kakedashi no namida
These are my first tears
駆け出しのナミダ
kitai mo yami no owari mo iranai
I don't need expectations or an end to the darkness
期待も闇も終わりもいらない
zero ni nareba
When all goes back to zero,
ゼロになれば　裸足のphrase-1
hadashi no brave one
I walk barefoot, and with courage
トリルラン卿　ご無事で
Sir Trillram!
You're safe!
嫌味か貴様
Shut your idiot mouth!
今まで何をしていた
Where the hell were you?
I-I was making repairs to the sky carrier.
ス…スカイキャリアの応急修理を
Take me to it. We're getting out of here!
案内しろ　さっさとここを離れるぞ
お待ちください
Wait, sir!
P-Princess Asseylum is alive!
ア…アセイラム姫が　生きておられます
How—
どういう事か…
I know!
知ってるよ
Which is why I'm going to kill her for good this time!
だから殺すのだ　今度こそ確実にな
How slow can you be, you brainless fool?
どこまで愚かなのだ　劣等人種
あれを生かしておけば　我らは一族郎党逆賊であろうが
If I let her live, my entire clan will be branded traitors!
Let's go.
行くぞ
You little rat.
貴様　何のつもりだ
What do you think you're doing?
Give me that.
よこ…
あのパレードは…
The parade...
姫様を　暗殺しようとしたのは…
You were the ones who tried to assassinate the princess!
後悔…　するぞ
You'll... regret this...